[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Every year at Ba Vang, I
mỗi dịp đầu năm đến với Ba Vàng tôi lại
have the opportunity to enjoy a dish
có dịp thưởng thức lại món ăn chứa đựng
full of childhood memories: rice balls with sesame seeds. Back then, when
đầy kỷ niệm tuổi thơ cơm nắm mối vừng
meat and fish were scarce, it was
ngày xưa thua còn thiếu thốn thịt cá là
a luxury. Our mothers and
một điều gì đó rất xa xỉ khi ấy các bà
grandmothers created countless
các mẹ đã sáng tạo ra biết bao món ăn
simple, rustic dishes from readily available ingredients, providing
dân dã từ những nguyên liệu đơn sơ sẵn
warmth and delicious meals for the family.
có giúp gia đình vừa Ấm bụng lại vừa
Visiting Ba Vang and trying the
ngon miệng đến thăm ba vàng ăn thử chiếc
fragrant rice balls with sesame seeds brings back
cơm nắm cùng mối vừng thơm phức những kỷ
childhood memories of cutting grass and going to
niệm tuổi thơ Trăn Châu cắt cỏ rồi cùng
school. The winter wind blows fiercely, the bamboo shoots rustle
đến trường lại ùa về trời mùa đông gió
outside, and in the
Bắc thổi lồng lộng bút giá ngoài hiên
small, warm kitchen, Mother Giang roasts peanuts and sesame seeds
trong gian bếp nhỏ ấm áp mẹ Giang lạc
to make the fragrant sesame seed rice balls to eat
rang vừng thơm lừng để làm mối vừng ăn
with sticky white rice. Back then, a rice ball mixed with
với cơm trắng dẻo thời ấy có nắm cơm độn
cassava to take to school for lunch was already very
sắn để mang đi học ăn bữa trưa đã thấy
satisfying. Now, with a stable economy and a
thỏa mãn lắm rồi giờ thì kinh tế ổn định
comfortable life, I seem to have
cuộc sống đầy đủ rồi nên dường như tôi
forgotten about this childhood dish. Even though it
cũng quên mất món ăn tuổi thơ Như vậy dù
's just a dish, I find
chỉ là một món ăn thôi Nhưng tôi thấy
the temple quite thoughtful, making
nhà chùa khá tinh tế bởi làm cho người
people feel a sense of warmth and familiarity, like
ta cảm nhận sự ấm áp thân thuộc như một
returning to childhood, reuniting with
lần được trở về tuổi thơ đoàn tụ bên ông
grandparents and parents in simple
bà bố mẹ trong những bữa ăn tuy đơn sơ
but heartfelt meals.  Love overflows! Indeed, the spirit of Tet (Vietnamese New Year) is
nhưng tình yêu thương thì ngập tràn Đúng
not just about reunions, but also about filling
là vị Tết không chỉ gặp mặt mà còn lấp
everyone's hearts with the warmth of family. If you have the chance to return to Ba Vang at
tâm thức mỗi người nếu có dịp về ba vàng
the beginning of the year, don't miss
đầu năm mọi người đừng bỏ qua món ăn
this familiar dish!
thân thuộc này